<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<journal>
<title>Tehran University Medical Journal</title>
<title_fa>مجله دانشکده پزشکی، دانشگاه علوم پزشکی تهران</title_fa>
<short_title>Tehran Univ Med J</short_title>
<subject>Medical Sciences</subject>
<web_url>http://tumj.tums.ac.ir</web_url>
<journal_hbi_system_id>1</journal_hbi_system_id>
<journal_hbi_system_user>admin</journal_hbi_system_user>
<journal_id_issn>1683-1764</journal_id_issn>
<journal_id_issn_online>1735-7322</journal_id_issn_online>
<journal_id_pii></journal_id_pii>
<journal_id_doi>10.18869/acadpub.tumj</journal_id_doi>
<journal_id_iranmedex></journal_id_iranmedex>
<journal_id_magiran></journal_id_magiran>
<journal_id_sid>000</journal_id_sid>
<journal_id_nlai>000</journal_id_nlai>
<journal_id_science>000</journal_id_science>
<language>fa</language>
<pubdate>
	<type>jalali</type>
	<year>1402</year>
	<month>7</month>
	<day>1</day>
</pubdate>
<pubdate>
	<type>gregorian</type>
	<year>2023</year>
	<month>10</month>
	<day>1</day>
</pubdate>
<volume>81</volume>
<number>7</number>
<publish_type>online</publish_type>
<publish_edition>1</publish_edition>
<article_type>fulltext</article_type>
<articleset>
	<article>


	<language>other</language>
	<article_id_doi></article_id_doi>
	<title_fa>تقویت بنیه دفاعی در مقابل بیوتروریسم، استفاده از مدل‌های حیوانی برای 
تولید دارو و واکسن ویروسی: یک مقاله مروری</title_fa>
	<title>Enhancing bioterrorism defense, leveraging animal models for
 viral drug and vaccine development: a review article</title>
	<subject_fa></subject_fa>
	<subject></subject>
	<content_type_fa>مقاله مروري</content_type_fa>
	<content_type>Review Article</content_type>
	<abstract_fa>&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:yekanYW;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:12pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:102%&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;direction:rtl&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;unicode-bidi:embed&quot;&gt;&lt;span lang=&quot;FA&quot; style=&quot;font-size:10.0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:102%&quot;&gt;استفاده تعمدی یا تهدیدآمیز از ویروس&#8204;ها، باکتری&#8204;ها، توکسین&#8204;ها و یا مواد سمی تهیه شده از ارگانیسم&#8204;های زنده برای ایجاد مرگ&#8204;و&#8204;میر یا بیماری&#8204;زایی در انسان، حیوانات و گیاهان، بیوتروریسم نام دارد. می&#8204;توان این عوامل را با پاشیدن آنها در هوا یا از طریق ایجاد عفونت در حیوانات و انتقال این عفونت به انسان یا از راه آلوده کردن منابع آب و غذا پخش کرد. اقدامات دفاعی، مانند واکنش اضطراری به &#8204;این نوع تروریسم، ناآشنا و ناشناخته است. حالت کلی درماندگی ناشی از &lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;کمبود&lt;/span&gt; آمادگی کامل و راهبردهای ضد&#8204;آلودگی، موضوع را پیچیده&#8204;تر می&#8204;کند. توانایی و علاقه گسترده پرسنل غیر&#8204;نظامی برای مشارکت در توسعه سلاح&#8204;های شیمیایی و بیولوژیکی مستقیما با دسترسی آسان به برتری دانشگاهی در سراسر جهان مرتبط است. عامل دیگر سواستفاده وسوسه&#8204;انگیز از داده&#8204;ها و دانش الکترونیکی رایگان در دسترس در مورد تولید آنتی&#8204;بیوتیک&#8204;ها و واکسن&#8204;ها و سلاح&#8204;های متعارف با جزییات مختلف پیچیده آنهاست. استفاده از حیوانات در تحقیقات آزمایشگاهی برای درک بهتر مکانیسم&#8204;&#8204; بیماری&#8204;ها، درمان و غلبه &#8204;بر محدودیت آزمایش&#8204;های بالینی سابقه طولانی دارد. پژوهشگران باید درک و شناخت درستی از انواع مدل&#8204;های حیوانی داشته باشند تا بتوانند با یک انتخاب صحیح و درست، درک بهتری از علایم بالینی بیماری&#8204;های ویروسی و برآیند و گزینه&#8204;های احتمالی برای درمان و ابداع واکسن ارایه&#8204;دهند. هدف از مطالعه پیش رو ارایه مدل&#8204;های حیوانی بیماری&#8204;های ویروسی انسانی برای بررسی کارایی داروها و واکسن&#8204;های ویروسی نوپدید و بازپدید است&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;LTR&quot; style=&quot;font-size:10.0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:102%&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang=&quot;FA&quot; style=&quot;font-size:10.0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:102%&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:&quot;B Lotus&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;</abstract_fa>
	<abstract>&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:12pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:130%&quot;&gt;&lt;span new=&quot;&quot; roman=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;font-family:&quot; times=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:10.0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:130%&quot;&gt;Deliberate or threatening use of viruses, bacteria, toxins, or poisonous substances prepared from living organisms to cause death or disease in humans, animals, and plants is called bioterrorism. These agents can be spread by spraying them in the air, causing infection in animals, transferring this infection to humans, or contaminating water and food sources. Defense measures, such as emergency responses to this type of terrorism, are unfamiliar and unknown. The general state of helplessness caused by the lack of complete preparation and the lack of anti-pollution strategies complicates the issue. The ability and widespread interest of civilian personnel to participate in the development of chemical and biological weapons is directly related to easy access to academic excellence around the world. Another factor is the tempting misuse of freely available electronic data and knowledge about the production of antibiotics, vaccines, and conventional weapons with their various complex details. The use of animals in laboratory research to better understand the mechanisms of disease and treatment and to overcome the limitations of clinical trials has a long history. For many viruses, laboratory diagnostic methods and reagents must be continuously modified to account for genetic variations and variants. Unlike bacterial diseases, many of which can be treated with antimicrobial drugs, there are fewer medical countermeasures to combat viral infections. Many of these pathogens are lethal or cause debilitating diseases in humans, making it ethically inappropriate to test the effectiveness of these countermeasures on human volunteers. Researchers must have a correct understanding of various animal models so that they can make the correct choice, gain a better understanding of the clinical symptoms of viral diseases, and provide possible options for treatment and vaccine development. It should be noted that decision-making when faced with a biological attack should be done away from too much fear, and this requires researchers to have prior knowledge of facing these threats. Despite all these checks and measures taken in advance, the international preparedness against these attacks is weak, which can be attributed to the lack of global plans to deal with the epidemic.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</abstract>
	<keyword_fa>مدل‌های حیوانی, بیوتروریسم, دارو, واکسن, بیماری‌های ویروسی.</keyword_fa>
	<keyword>animal models, bioterrorism, drug, vaccine, viral diseases.</keyword>
	<start_page>470</start_page>
	<end_page>485</end_page>
	<web_url>http://tumj.tums.ac.ir/browse.php?a_code=A-10-3666-696&amp;slc_lang=other&amp;sid=1</web_url>


<author_list>
	<author>
	<first_name>Hadi</first_name>
	<middle_name></middle_name>
	<last_name>Lotfi</last_name>
	<suffix></suffix>
	<first_name_fa>هادی</first_name_fa>
	<middle_name_fa></middle_name_fa>
	<last_name_fa>لطفی</last_name_fa>
	<suffix_fa></suffix_fa>
	<email></email>
	<code></code>
	<orcid></orcid>
	<coreauthor>Yes
</coreauthor>
	<affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology, sabzevar University of Medical Science, Sabzevar, Iran.</affiliation>
	<affiliation_fa>گروه میکروبیولوژی، دانشکده پزشکی، دانشگاه علوم پزشکی سبزوار، سبزوار، ایران.</affiliation_fa>
	 </author>


	<author>
	<first_name>Morteza</first_name>
	<middle_name></middle_name>
	<last_name>Izadi</last_name>
	<suffix></suffix>
	<first_name_fa>مرتضی</first_name_fa>
	<middle_name_fa></middle_name_fa>
	<last_name_fa>ایزدی</last_name_fa>
	<suffix_fa></suffix_fa>
	<email></email>
	<code></code>
	<orcid></orcid>
	<coreauthor>No</coreauthor>
	<affiliation>Health Research Center, Baqiyatallah University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</affiliation>
	<affiliation_fa>مرکز تحقیقات سلامت، دانشگاه علوم پزشکی بقیه الله عج، تهران، ایران.</affiliation_fa>
	 </author>


	<author>
	<first_name>Ehsan</first_name>
	<middle_name></middle_name>
	<last_name>Lutfi </last_name>
	<suffix></suffix>
	<first_name_fa>احسان</first_name_fa>
	<middle_name_fa></middle_name_fa>
	<last_name_fa>لطفی</last_name_fa>
	<suffix_fa></suffix_fa>
	<email></email>
	<code></code>
	<orcid></orcid>
	<coreauthor>No</coreauthor>
	<affiliation>Applied Virology Research Center, Baqiyatallah University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</affiliation>
	<affiliation_fa>مرکز تحقیقات ویروس شناسی کاربردی، دانشگاه علوم پزشکی بقیه الله عج، تهران، ایران.</affiliation_fa>
	 </author>


	<author>
	<first_name>Hadi </first_name>
	<middle_name></middle_name>
	<last_name>Esmaeili Gouvarchin Ghaleh</last_name>
	<suffix></suffix>
	<first_name_fa>هادی</first_name_fa>
	<middle_name_fa></middle_name_fa>
	<last_name_fa>اسمعیلی گورچین قلعه</last_name_fa>
	<suffix_fa></suffix_fa>
	<email>h.smaili69@yahoo.com</email>
	<code></code>
	<orcid></orcid>
	<coreauthor>No</coreauthor>
	<affiliation>Applied Virology Research Center, Baqiyatallah University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</affiliation>
	<affiliation_fa>مرکز تحقیقات ویروس شناسی کاربردی، دانشگاه علوم پزشکی بقیه الله عج، تهران، ایران.</affiliation_fa>
	 </author>


</author_list>


	</article>
</articleset>
</journal>
